It's another question.
Spontaneously, I seek to free myself from attachment to
I seek to free myself from attachment to
my identity,
above all, my gender.
This is from a woman. Uh-huh. My life
has been steeped in sexism,
Mhm. where womanhood is cast as frail,
foolish, vain, inferior.
At times I let such words drift past me,
mere echoes of ignorance, but other
times they wound me deeply, making me
resent my own birth. Mhm.
I know this attachment is
uh to identities dukkha, dukkha, yet
detachment eludes me. How does one
remain unmoved when prejudice is not
mere illusion, but rooted in biological
differences that others scorn? Mhm.
Is my reasoning flawed, or is true
equanimity beyond reach?
No, it's not beyond reach, you know, but
it's In order to reach it,
In order to reach it,
you might have to
give up
more than you're willing to.
Because, um
See, the world can think one thing or
the other thing
about your birth,
Mhm. caste, Mhm. clanhood, gender.
But fundamentally, the only reason that
praise and blame
affects you
is cuz you're taking it up as yours.
So, each time you feel affected because
each time you feel affected because
somebody said something negative about
your gender
is cuz you're taking up that gender as
yours. As I also how do I take the gender? How
As I also how do I take the gender? How
do I take it up? Can I just say no to
it? It's like, well, you can, but that won't
It's like, well, you can, but that won't
work.
Cuz taking it up, it's not like a a
conscious repetitive mental decision
that you just sit one day and say,
"Today I'll decide to take it up."
No, you take it up through your acts.
So, are you taking up your body
as the basis of pleasure,
as the basis of ownership,
as the basis of proliferation of
desires, sight, sound, smell, taste, touches? You
sight, sound, smell, taste, touches? You
are taking up the ownership of whatever
the body is, whatever that body is
deemed to be by others in the society.
Mhm. So, that's what I mean, like,
you can find equanimity, but you need to
basically, as the Buddha said, you need
to be developed in regard to your own
body internally. In other words, you need to
internally. In other words, you need to
fully
um abandon the slightest traces of
ownership. They would have been uh
proliferated and maintained through the
acts of desire, your will, control,
uh safety that you find in the body. Um
so, that's why the reflections the Buddha
that's why the reflections the Buddha
was recommending, it's like,
um you need to regard your own body
internally, whether others approve of it
or not, whether they praise your gender
or not.
You yourself need to regard it as a Oh,
this is a trap. Every time I give in to
the physical desires, physical acts
of distraction and so on, I am accepting
it at a face value. So, even if I wish
to not be moved by praise or blame
directed towards my external form, I
will be cuz I've taken it up.
So, you need to go deep in order to
basically, um
uproot that trap that you keep taking up
at face value mistakenly. And then,
whether the whole world praises you or
blames you, it won't be a problem cuz
it's like, literally, it has nothing to
do with you.
They're praising something that has
circumstantially arisen, or they're
blaming something that has
circumstantially arisen.
So, the only reason you're moving you
you're being moved by it now is cuz you
are very much have taken it up, and you
don't know how to let go of it cuz you
think letting go of it is on some sort
of level of some determination decision
that you need to make in regard to it.
But it's not. It's through purification
of your acts
that perpetuate the ownership,
perpetuate the desire, perpetuate the
basis of um accepting this body cuz it
serves me
for this or that when I want it.
So, yeah,
you need to see how far you want to go.
So, you make yourself liable to those uh
to praise and blame, to the worldly
winds, as the sutras say. Because
delighting in your body, taking up
Taking up, delighting in it, yeah. Yeah,
it's not that Yeah. praise and blame is
the cause of your issue.
the the secondary issues that arise on
account of it. If your body is not taken
up
through the careless actions rooted in
greed, aversion, distraction,
Mhm. even as I said, even if you haven't made
even as I said, even if you haven't made
a conscious decision to not be bothered
by what others say, you won't be
bothered by what others say.
You got to
Cuz it's not yours anymore, basically.
There is no identification with it
anymore. Cuz obviously, this person who asked the
Cuz obviously, this person who asked the
question recognizes that identification
with the body is the problem. Mhm.
But to me, it sounds as if that they
still hope that there is something they
can just do on top of it that will
unplug that identification. It's like,
no, you got to undo everything
that you have now. Your entire
relationship internally with your own
body has to be rewritten.
That's why it just feels easier
for people to just, well, no, let's just
address the society Mhm. and change
everyone's mind
about gender or about caste or about
whatever. And
And
this is the extension of the problem.
Even if you get it your way, even if you
get everybody to respect you for what
you are, however you were born,
you're still taking it up gratuitously.
You're taking up that which has which is
circumstantially arisen, that which does
is going to is going to lead to uh
destruction and disintegration. You are
still taking it up there. So, if now
you're not affected by the words of
others in regard to your body or gender
or whatever, you'll be affected by
something else.
Because it is out there in the world
that you are do you have no control
over, even if you get some degree of
uh everybody agreeing
uh you know, how to talk about it, how
to address it, what to think about it,
there's always going to be something
else that's going to be at odds with it.
that's going to be at odds with it.
So, if it's not gender, the body is just
going to be something else.
But fundamentally, it's all rooted in
the problem of taking up what is not
yours, what cannot even be yours, and
you refuse to give it up. So, instead
you want to tailor the environment to
keep supporting it and not contradicting
it.
I said there's there's not one form that
the Buddha said, there's not one
type of form that doesn't cause, well,
that's not suffering when one's
delighting in it.
Yeah, cuz it's subject to change
cuz it's subject to change
from the very beginning.
But if one is not delighting
And it always remains, see, like, even
if you get the whole society, say, to
approve of the way you were born and
everybody to praise it, even. Mhm.
The lingering possibility always remains
that somebody might not do it.
And that's already going to reveal you
the whole weight that rides on it, even
um it's going to basically make you feel
just the possibility that somebody might
still disapprove of you
will bother you as much as the actual
disapproval used to bother you. Cuz it
reveals the same thing. It's unownable,
yet you refuse to let go of it because
it's too terrifying to think of, well,
how would I live without um
desires, without satisfying my desires,
without giving in to the uh
distractions. How will I live without
using this body to get what I want?
That just feels like, oh,
well, like an abyss, as the sutras describe.
like an abyss, as the sutras describe.
The idea of not following physical
desires, not acting out of body unwholesomely,
not acting out of body unwholesomely,
to to to people that are that are like
householders and not
uh not um
not practicing restraint, that feels
like a sudden precipice. Like, feels
like the end of life, almost.
But the only reason it feels like that
is cuz just you refuse to even consider
the alternative of giving it all up.
So, then, as I said, you're left in this
state of conflict
of this which is unownable,
that I know I shouldn't be identified
with, I can't help by being identified
with, and I kind of recognize that's why
I'm bothered by things.
Um that's cuz being elated on account of
praise, it's equal bother. It's actually
even worse.
You know, if somebody's just criticizing
you, it outlines the problem for you,
the problem of identification with the
body that's being fully criticized and
attacked. If somebody praises you,
that's even stickier, even slimier, even
harder to get rid of your own delight in
that acceptance.
Uh praise is traps you even Well, yeah,
cuz see, on top of already not being
able to not accept the body at the face
value, the senses at the face value,
the extension of the approval of that,
someone's praise, is just going to be
twice as much acceptance now that you
just can't help. Yeah.
So, that's why it's like, oh, I should
actually be more concerned
about being praised
than about being criticized on account
of my immutable characteristic that I'm
born with. It constantly
Cuz being criticized just outlines the
extent of the body that I have no
control over. I don't want it to be this
way, but if I'm affected, it means I'm
taking it up in other ways, and now that
I'm affected
as a result of that.
You get to see that more clearly. But praise
But praise
But if you're all all you're getting is
praise, Yeah, fools you, basically. It fools
Yeah, fools you, basically. It fools
you, yeah, yeah. You have no reason to
really dig deep.
And that's kind of
the the the practical purpose of the
precept of purification
and and embellishing of your form, you
know, to
clothing, dresses, whatever.
It's cuz see, when people are dependent
on their presentation of this body
towards others,
Mhm. they're going to feel equally
anxious, equally undermined
if they go in the public without the
makeup, without the nice clothes.
Cuz now what others think about it
affects me to my core.
In other words, it shows you
how deeply unknowable that which you
so thoroughly take to be yours is,
this body.
So giving up the beautification might
seem like a random thing, but actually
for many people they do depend on their
presentation. That's the level of how
far their identity has sort of
proliferated. So by not making yourself
So by not making yourself
presentable in what you deem an
agreeable way, I don't mean like go
around like dirty or filthy.
But that's quite a clear line between,
okay, just
be clean or something, but are you now
beautifying it? Are you now emphasizing
your form in other ways, in other
pleasing ways to be more accepted or
liked or admired? All of that is the
extension of that same trying to get
that which is deeply not yours
through approval of others to be yours.
To confirm that that is yours cuz I
can't help but regard it as mine,
although deep down I know it's not. It
cannot be.
So that's why the beautification, the
adornment, the presentation in a in a
kind of selective way,
those are all your acts and choices and
you need to give that up.
And then, oh, look,
nobody likes me.
Nobody approves of this. They might even
hate it. It's like, yeah, now that's
revealing even more.
That there is no reason for you to
entertain the ownership of that.
Cuz if it needs beautification and
deceit, well, means that's not what it really
well, means that's not what it really
is.
And that's why even that the sutra say,
like a young man or a woman should
regard their own body in the same way
they would regard a dead snake wrapped
around their neck.
Like if they see themselves in the
mirror, it should be like, oh, this is
that that
unappealing form.
But that will become more and more
apparent if you would have stopped
giving in to like
as I said,
cover up, specifications, presentations,
the way that you know, the society wants
it or you want society to want it or
whatever. So if you just have like a basic, as I
So if you just have like a basic, as I
said, common sense,
yes, you know,
dress up normally,
plainly, not not trying to increase or emphasize
not not trying to increase or emphasize
certain aspects of the body that people
might deem um
nice, just leave it as it is.
You are already distancing yourself from
it. You're already not adding more fuel
to that gratuitous identification that
you shouldn't have been doing in the
first place.
Well, getting closer to a proper
perspective, yeah.
It's not going to resolve the problem,
but it's certainly not going to make it
worse.
You're not emphasizing the wrong things
anymore. Yeah, which you would have been
doing only because you refuse to give up
the pleasure you get through it and your
implicit identification with it.